Preliminary Guide to the Elizabeth C. Alden Papers, 1970s-2000s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Elizabeth C. Alden papers 1970s-2000s
Alden, Elizabeth C.
3.4 linear feet Extent: 1344 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00021
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The items in this collection were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke from Perkins Library in 1983 as part of a project to cull the library's backlog of pamphlets.
Biographical Note
Alden holds degrees from Duke University and Colorado College, as well as advanced degrees from Indiana University, and the SMU Perkins School of Theology. She is currently (1998) Coordinator for Service-Learning for the Kenan Ethics Program.
Collection Overview
This unprocessed accession is comprised primarily of published materials (magazines, newsletters, and photocopies and clippings of newspaper and magazine articles) and of a few manuscript items related to women's employment, religious, legal, and domestic issues. The papers document Rev. Alden's feminist activism during the 1970s and early 1980s while she was living in Texas. Rev. Alden's folder titles and original arrangement of items were maintained. This collection is open for use.
Subject Headings
Alden, Elizabeth C.; Activists -- Texas; Women's rights -- Religious aspects; Women's rights and spiritualism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women -- Employment -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Domestic relations -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Contents of Collection
- Accession (1998-0018)
  - Liberation Movement (Box 1)
  - Women's Liberation (Box 1)
  - Resources (Box 1)
  - Vacation (Box 1)
  - Cosrow, Minutes, 1977, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Cosrow, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Women in the Church (Ministry and Lay) (Box 1)
  - Commission on the Status and Role of Women (Box 1)
  - Women in Media (Box 1)
  - Women in Media: Shaping Our Future, 1981, May 31 (Box 1)
  - Women: Worship (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Marriage (Box 1)
  - Marriage: Services and Contracts (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous '70s article on women (Box 1)
  - Children (Box 1)
  - Youth: Colloquy (Box 1)
  - Youth: Creative Workshop; Culture and Education (Box 1)
  - Youth (Box 1)
  - Parenting (Box 1)
  - Family (Box 1)
  - "Daughters of Sarah" and Ecumenical Women's Center Publications (Box 1)
  - Sexist Language in the Church (Box 1)
  - Feminist Theology (Box 1)
  - Feminism and the Bible (Box 1)
  - Ministry Mystique: Notes for Women's Forum (Box 1)
  - Clergy Women: Sexual Harrassment Consultation, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Women in the Church: Issues; Lang.--Role Stereotypes (Box 1)
  - Abortion and Birth Control (Box 1)
  - Women: Ads (Box 1)
  - The Ann Landers Encyclopedia (Box 1)
  - Battered Women and Children (Box 1)
  - Black Women (Box 1)
  - COSROW (Box 1)
  - Women Clergy (and Church Women) (Box 2)
  - Displaced Homemakers (Box 2)
  - Divorce (Box 2)
  - ERA (Box 2)
  - Equal Rights (Box 2)
  - Equal Times, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Everywoman Center (Box 2)
  - Family Place (Box 2)
  - Famous Women (Box 2)
  - Feminism (Box 2)
  - Film & Drama & Adventure (Box 2)
  - Husbands (Box 2)
  - I Want a Wife (Box 2)
  - Women's Images (Box 2)
  - JEW--Escape (Box 2)
  - Living Together (Box 2)
- Accession (2005-0043), (1 box) (Box 2)
  Addition (05-043) (200 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1970-1994) is comprised of subject files pertaining to homophobia, abortion, and a women's church conference held April 16-18, 1993, in Albuquerque, NM; also includes notes, brochures, articles, and clippings. This accession is closed to researchers.
- Accession (2006-0072), (1 box) (Box 2)
  Addition (06-072) (44 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated 1985-1993) consists of clippings, newsletters, and periodicals related to women's issues, feminism, and religion.
- Accession (2009-0166), (1 box) (Box 2)
  Addition (2009-0166) (200 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1970-2007) includes pamphlets, programs, and publications from Alden's work with the Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights and other women's and clergy groups.
  - Programs and pamphlets, 1998-2007 (Box 1)
  - Peace conference, Dallas, 8 August 1988 (Box 1)
  - RCAR (Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights), 1991 (Box 1)
  - Sexual abuse in the clergy (Box 1)
  - New Mexico Women's Foundation, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Iowa Clergy Consultation Service on Problem Pregnancy, Adoption, and Abortion, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Males and the Feminist Movements, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Church Women United (Box 1)
  - Divinity School women's center (Box 1)
  - Hot Flash, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Women clergy: articles, brochures, pamphlets, 1970s-1990s (Box 1)